Rajeev Jain

Principal Research Software Developer · Argonne National Laboratory · Mathematics and Computer Science

↑ rajeeja@gmail.com □ +1 312-725-3380 in linkedin poogle scholar points grouped in the google scholar poogle sc

Summary

I have 14 years of experience managing/developing software projects. Over the years I have been working on a variety of fields from AI, Urban, Nuclear, Climate, Astrophysics and even Cancer, the common theme tying all these broad topics is computation, simulation and optimization. I am interested in software development, AI, blockchain and managing multi-disciplinary simulation/computation for applications-oriented problems.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2018 - 2022 Principal Research Software Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

- ⇒ Managed junior developers and also developed code for deep neural network (DNN) models in python.
- ⇒ Delivered new end-to-end functionality from conceptualization to actual coding.
- ⇒ Handled complex compute performance related issues and optimized code. Wrote distribute toolset for parallel applications.
- ⇒ Authored a paper: "Supporting a Community of Cancer Models with the CANDLE Checkpoint Module", this enables a standard to way to save pytorch and tensorflow based checkpoint files for restarting DNN models.

2011 – 2018 Software Development Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

- ⇒ Handled the coupled urban exascale simulation project, lead a diverse team of experts from different national labs and universities.
- ⇒ My reactor generator tool was used by Kitware Inc. to write and get SBIR funding Phase 1 for \$225k and Phase 2 for \$750k for a 2 year period. They developed GUI and added some new features to the toolset.
- ⇒ Lead the development of MeshKit, presented yearly updates to scientific funding agencies in Washington D.C. office.

2009 – 2011 Pre-doctoral Appointee, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

- ⇒ Presented my work in leading peer-reviewed conferences and also wrote funding proposals to the Department of Energy Offices.
- ⇒ Gathered requirement and built the reactor geometry and mesh generation tool.

Research and Teaching Assistant, Civil Engineering in the School of Sustainable Engineering and the Built
2007 – 2009 Environment ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY

- ⇒ Mentored students to solve structural engineering problems and graded assignements.
- ⇒ Wrote multidisciplinary, scalable code for running simulation jobs in distributed systems.

2006 – 2007 **Project Engineer**, SAP/Java Wipro Technologies, Bangalore/Hyderabad, India

- ⇒ Complete Java programming course and worked on a mobile payment systems for Nokia (Bangalore)
- ⇒ 3 months training in SAP ABAP and started working in a project with Kodak (Hyderabad)

Research Trainee, Engineering Research Division Tata Motors, Pune, India

⇒ Performed hot and cold circuit automobile engine fitted with retarder.

Summer 2004 Trainee Process Engineer, Research and Development BHILAI STEEL PLANT, BHILAI, INDIA

⇒ Understood and learned testing of railway tracks, performed a study to find bottlenecks in the entire process.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS

Summer 2005

2020 – present Co-Developer, UXarray GITHUB LINK

Helped design and code the first draft of the UXARRAY API, wrote python functions to integrate and read/write unstructured grids.

Rajeev Jain Curriculum Vitæ

2016 - present Co-Developer, ECP-CANDLE

GITHUB LINK

Published papers on model robustness with counterfactuals / noise injection and hyper-parameter optimization framework "Supervisor". Currently focussed on testing claims made by the recent cancer drug-response papers, creating a framework for understanding model sensitivity and XAI

2018 – present Co-Developer, Flash-X

DOCUMENTATION

Designed/coded asynchronous write and compression of HDF5 checkpoint file. Help with performance benchmarking on DOE supercomputers, CI, documentation. Review/manage GitHub policies, actions, PRs, issues etc.

2009 – 2016 Lead Developer, MeshKit

BITBUCKET LINK

Principal Investigator for MeshKit (mesh generation C++ toolkit) for the reactor geometry generation package. Wrote several mesh/geometry generation algorithms and published in peer-reviewed conferences/journals.

EDUCATION

2017 – 2020 Masters of Science Computer Science

University of Chicago

2007 – 2009 Master of Science Structural Engg. (Minor Computer Science)

Arizona State University

Thesis title: "Blast Mitigation solutions via FEM-Based Design Optimization."

2002 – 2006 B.Tech Mechanical Engineering

IIT Dhanbad, India

Honors

2010 – present Mentor, Supervised several summer students/postdocs and staff members Argonne National Laboratory

NUMGRID 2020 Invited: Program Committee Member, Managed and reviewed papers

Reviewer and Session Chair Computational Geometries, SNA and MC conference

2015-2017 **Mentor** KITWARE INC. FOR SBIR PHASE I AND II

Basis of this work was my tool RGG, click for details

2007 – 2009 University Graduate Fellowship, \$4000 ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY

2004 – 2004 Ist Prize for Low Budget Car Design Contest, INR 40k+ TECH FEST IIT KHARAGPUR AND MINDA LTD. DELHI

OTHER SKILLS AND ACTIVITIES

1990-present Cricket: Playing and watching